<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation or edict Touching the opening and restoring of the traffique, and commerce of Spain, with these countries: although they haue seuered themselues from the obeisance of the illustrous arch-duke, as also vvith all vassals and subiects of princes and common-weales, being their friends, or neutrals. Faithfully translated out of the Nether-landish tongue according to printed copy. Imprinted at Brussels.</title>
            <author>Netherlands. Sovereign (1598-1621 : Albert and Isabella)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08110</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112765</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848010</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848010</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13082</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08110)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13082)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1636:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation or edict Touching the opening and restoring of the traffique, and commerce of Spain, with these countries: although they haue seuered themselues from the obeisance of the illustrous arch-duke, as also vvith all vassals and subiects of princes and common-weales, being their friends, or neutrals. Faithfully translated out of the Nether-landish tongue according to printed copy. Imprinted at Brussels.</title>
                  <author>Netherlands. Sovereign (1598-1621 : Albert and Isabella)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By E. Allde] for Thomas Archer and are to be solde at the little shop by the Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  Commerce --  Spain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13082:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Proclamation or Edict. Touching the Opening and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Traffique, and Commerce of Spain, with theſe Countries: Although they haue ſeuered themſelues from the obeiſance of the Illuſtrous
<hi>Arch-Duke,</hi> As alſo with all Vaſſals and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of Princes and Common-weales, being their friends, or Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trals.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully Tranſlated out of the Nether-landiſh tongue according to printed Copy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>Bruſſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>Thomas Archer</hi> and are to be ſolde at the little ſhop by the Exchange. 1603.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="edict">
            <pb facs="tcp:13082:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13082:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>By the Arch-Duke.</head>
               <head>To our truſtie and wel-beloued, the Chancellors and Perſons of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile in <hi>Brabant:</hi> health.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ſo manifeſt, with what deſire, zeale, and care, the King (our beloued Lorde &amp; brother,) hath euer and yet doth ſeeke to further our helpe and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the good will which wee beare to the furtherance and welfare of our good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects: for, as much as in vs lyeth to redeeme and diſcharge them of the miſeries, inconueniences and ſuppreſſions which they haue &amp; do endure through the continuance of theſe long-laſting warres, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing them all benefites and eaſements, in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of their fedilitie. Wee then deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring like wiſe the quiet and aduauncement of the other our Vaſſals of the Iles of
<hi>Holand</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> and other Prouinces, ſeperated from the obedience, which as their Soueraigne and naturall Princes they owe vnto vs, being deceiued and ſeduced by ſome ill-willers, who for their owne benefite haue and doe yet hold them in ſo great oppreſſion.</p>
               <p>And marking the miſeries &amp; oppreſſions which they endure, with all the intollerable taxes which they wring from them, vnder the falſe collour of warre, into the which they haue caſt themſelues, vnder the pretence of the preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, taking away their ſubſtance and meanes, <pb facs="tcp:13082:3"/>and reducing them to an vtter pouertie &amp; diſpaire, ouer ſhadowing &amp; concealing the good will which we haue to the furtherance of their welfare and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe, and to draw them out of the bondage and oppreſſion wherein at this preſent they remaine: for it is certaine, that all the euils and miſchiefes which are hapened by reaſon of theſe ſaide warres and diſobediences (together with the bloodſheades which to our great griefe hath enſued thereon, and as yet are continuing) do not proceede from the will of our Vaſſals, but from the bad heartes of ſuch as haue taken and vſurped all authoritie and Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne gouernment, as alſo from the ſubtilties and lyes wherwith they entertaine them, ſucking and drawing all their meanes and ſubſtance from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: therewith to make their owne priuate benefite and gaine, to the great diſaduancement of the Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie, and to maintaine themſelues in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide authority.</p>
               <p>To the ende therefore that they may manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee and perceaue, what loue and affection wee beare them, wee haue reſolued to ſuffer and permit them the trade and Nauigation which we hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue prohibited them, in the Prouinces of our obediences: As alſo at our requeſt and in our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and reſpect, they haue beene done by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in his Realmes of <hi>Spaine,</hi> according to the Declaration, publiſhed by his certaine command and Edict, and ſent vnto vs in the ſpaniſh tongue: whereof the tranſlation followeth from worde to worde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="edict">
                           <pb facs="tcp:13082:3"/>
                           <head>By the Kings Maieſtie.</head>
                           <p>
                              <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>hereas I haue taken regarde that through the continuation of the wars riſen in the <hi>Neither-lands</hi> and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces of <hi>Flanders,</hi> by ſome ſubiectes, the which by bad counſell are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne from their due obedience, drawing to them a great number of the good and obedient Vaſſals, there haue enſued great hurtes and effuſions of blood ſince theſe 36. yeares paſt, and that thereby hath beene introduced great and dangerous muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Policie and good gouernement. Alſo that the old and auncient traine and courſe of trade hath thereby beene greatly broken and inuerted, drawing the ſame out of the hands of the good &amp; obedient ſubiects of the ſaid Prouinces: whereas heeretofore was vſed to bee the greateſt trade as well of the marchandiſes which were brought out of theſe our Realmes, Lands, and Dominions, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the North partes, and others: As alſo for thoſe which from the aforeſaid parts were brought into the ſaid <hi>Neither-lands:</hi> and theſe our ſayde Realmes, Dominions, and others whereout are ſprung manifeſt diſorders and inconueniences.</p>
                           <p>And as wee deſire to reſtore and renewe the Commerce, and to ſet it in his forme, trayne, and order as heertofore it hath beene in the ſaid Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; eſpecially, in the hauens &amp; townes as yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining <pb facs="tcp:13082:4"/>vnder the due obedience of the illuſtrious Arch-duke, <hi>Albertus,</hi> and the <hi>Infanta,</hi> Lady
<hi>Iſabella,</hi> my brother and Siſter, to the wel-fare and profite of their obedient ſubiects as for the good and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded loue of the common good: ſeeing heerein the clemencie &amp; kindenes vnto which I am bound by the place whereunto it hath pleaſed th' Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie GOD to call me. And by the effects, to ſhewe the deſire which I haue alwaies had, to the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the common good, &amp; eſpeciallie of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Nether-lands: hauing communicated all the ſame vnto my abouenamed Brother and Siſter, and thereupon receaued th' aduice of our Counſaile of State, I haue reſolued to open and againe to raiſe vp, the aforeſaid trade of Marchandiſe, vpon the conditions and manner following.</p>
                           <p n="1">1 <hi>INprimis,</hi> I am content and ordaine, that all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of what quallitie and condition ſoeuer, as well of my Vaſſals and Subiects, as of other Princes &amp; Common-weales, my Friends, Allies, and Neutrals, although they were borne &amp; dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Iles of
<hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> and in the other Prouinces, which are fallen from the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience &amp; alleageance of my before-named Brother and Siſter, which ſtill come to trade, traffique and negotiate in my ſaid Kingdomes, and in the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens thereof (the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies</hi> and the Iles of <hi>Barlouent,</hi> with others by the Lawes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden excepted) may quietlie and marchant like come to vſe their trade and traffique, according to the lawes &amp; cuſtomes of theſe Kingdomes, in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the wares which they ſhall bring thither, <pb facs="tcp:13082:4"/>ſuch dueties as haue beene impoſed therevpon vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they day of the publication heereof, conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and vpon expreſſe charge, that they haue not nor ſhall not pay directly, nor indirectly any due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the enemies of this Crowne, of my ſaid bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Siſter, nor alſo to theſe of the Countries of <hi>Holand</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> and other Prouinces their adherents, fallen from their alleageance: vpon payne, that if at any time it ſhall bee prooued, that they haue payed any duetie to the ſaide diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents or to our enemies, ſuch marchandiſes ſhall be forfaited: and if in caſe they were ſolde or made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, the factor or perſon to whom they ſhould haue beene directed, and that ſhould haue ſolde the ſame, ſhall bee forced to repay the woorth of the ſame, without any acquitting, nor exception of perſons whatſoeuer.</p>
                           <p n="2">2 In like ſort, I will and ordaine, that all Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes not prohibited, which ſhalbe carried forth of theſe my Realmes, whether by Strangers or by the Naturalls thereof, towards any Countrey whatſoeuer, the places here-vnder ſpecified onely excepted, ſhall pay me
30. in the 100. The which I impoſe for a newe duetie of that which they ſhall conuay out, without any exceptions of perſons nor Marchandiſes, and this ouer and aboue the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie dueties eſtabliſhed vpon them vntill the day of the publication of this my Edict, all which Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes that ſhall bee conuayed out of theſe Realmes, ſhall be of ſuch, as by the lawes thereof ſhall not be forbidden or prohibited.</p>
                           <p n="3">3 As for the Traffique and Comerce with the Kingdomes, Countryes, and Eſtates, bordering <pb facs="tcp:13082:5"/>vpon the
<hi>Mediterranean-ſea,</hi> as well myne, as of my Friends and Allyes: my will is, That there be no Nouelties nor change made from that which hath bene heretofore vſed, as well in regard of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes, as for the dueties which are accuſtomed to be paide: vpon this condition alwaies, that all ſuch as ſhall lade for thoſe Countries and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, ſhall bee bound to put in ſecurity, within ſixe Moneths after the day of their departure from the Ports of this Realme, to preſent certificate of the Conſuls and perſons thereunto appointed, or to be appointed in the Portes of the ſaide Realmes, Countries and Eſtates of myne, my Friendes and allies, bordering vpon the <hi>Mediteranean-ſea,</hi> to haue liuered and diſcharged the ſaide Marchandiſes in thoſe partes for the which they had laden them, by meanes whereof they ſhall bee diſcharged of their ſayd ſuretieſhip or caution, without paying ought but the ordinary dueties, impoſed before the date hereof. And in default of preſenting the ſaide certificate, the ſaide ſureties ſhall be bound to pay 20. in the 100. of all the Marchandiſes which they ſhall haue remained out. And to the ende therein be no fraude vſed, it is declared that the Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Commerce of the ſaid Kingdomes, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and Eſtates of the <hi>Mediterranean-ſea,</hi> and of my Friends and allies, ſhall be from the Streights of
<hi>Gibraltar,</hi> towardes the partes of <hi>Leuant,</hi> and from them of the North vntill the ſaid Streights, for that if thoſe of the ſaide
<hi>Medite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ranean-ſea,</hi> doe paſſe aboue the ſaide Streightes, and doe lade in theſe Realmes of
<hi>Spaine</hi> and Iles thereof, for the North Countries, they ſhall not enioy the ſayde <pb facs="tcp:13082:5"/>Freedome, but ſhall be ſubiect to the charge decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the former chapter.</p>
                           <p n="4">4 In like maner, ſhall be free from the duetie of 30. in the 100. the Iron and Steele which ſhall be ſhipped out of the Prouince of <hi>Guipuzcoa,</hi> and Lordſhip of <hi>Biſcaye,</hi> the Mountaines and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>Nauarres</hi> for <hi>France,</hi> paying only the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie dueties, at the charge alwayes of the ſelfe ſame caution declared in the Chapter aboue.</p>
                           <p n="5">5 My will and pleaſure is, that all &amp; euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon &amp; perſons, which in the forme aboue ſaid man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhall come to trade in theſe my Kingdoms with their Shippes and Marchandiſes, and ſhall bind themſelues to conduct and diſcharge thoſe which they ſhall lade in them, in the Ports of the townes vnder the obedience of my ſayde Brother and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, without paying any thing directly or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to our enemies and diſobedient Subiects, ſhall be free and exempt of the ſaide duetie of 30. in the 100. without that they ſhall bee bound to pay any other but the ordinary dueties.</p>
                           <p n="6">6 And to the end that they may more eaſily do it and inioy the ſayd freedome, without paying the ſayd 30. in the 100. I command and ordaine, al Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of Iuſtice of theſe my Realmes and Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, freely to ſuffer all perſons to ſhip without paying any other then the ordinarie dueties, for all ſorts of marchandiſes, thoſe onely excepted which by the lawes of theſe Realmes are prohibited, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition that they ſet good &amp; ſufficient caution or ſecuritie before ſuch perſons which hereunto by me ſhall be ordained in my Portes: to preſent certification from the perſons which my ſaid Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <pb facs="tcp:13082:6"/>and Siſter there vnto ſhall appoint, to haue diſcharged the ſaide Marchandiſes franke and freely, in the ſayd Ports and Townes of their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, or ſuch part thereof, as they ſhall haue vnladen there, and that within ſixe moneths after their departure from my ſayd Ports: that then by vertue thereof, they ſhall remaine freed and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued of the ſaid caution or ſecuritie: By reaſon that by the ſaid certificate ſhall appeare that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they ſhall haue diſcharge there, and for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynder their Sureties ſhal pay the aforenamed duetie of thirtie in the hundred, which Certificate, ſhall bee giuen vnto them by the afore-named per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons without any trouble, or without demanding any duetie of them for the ſame.</p>
                           <p n="7">7 I defende, and ordeine expreſſely, that in theſe my Kingdoms by what meanes or way ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, be not brought either directly or indirectly, the Marchandiſes heere vnder declared, vnleſſe they be made and wrought in the obedient Prouinces of the
<hi>Nether-lands.</hi> (To wit:)</p>
                           <list>
                              <item>Hondſcote Sayes, and all maner of Sayet wares.</item>
                              <item>Little Cuſhions to ſowe, or otherwiſe.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <item>Points, and pinnes.</item>
                              <item>Starch.</item>
                              <item>Buratoes, and Taffatyes.</item>
                              <item>Cow-hydes,</item>
                              <item>Mokadoes.</item>
                              <item>Tryplt-Veluets.</item>
                              <item>Sarges, or Worſteds.</item>
                           </list>
                           <p>And other workes, the which are made at <hi>Lille,</hi> and <hi>Tournaye,</hi> Carpets.</p>
                           <list>
                              <pb facs="tcp:13082:6"/>
                              <item>Kettels, and Baſens.</item>
                           </list>
                           <p>Which are made in the ſaid <hi>Neither-lands,</hi> and at <hi>Axe,</hi> ſo farre foorth as they beare the marke of my ſayd Brother and Siſter.</p>
                           <list>
                              <item>Red Copper wrought.</item>
                              <item>Cambricke.</item>
                              <item>Woolen Stockings.</item>
                              <item>All manner of Kniues.</item>
                              <item>Cheſts or Coffers.</item>
                              <item>Pewter.</item>
                              <item>Wyer of Iron, and Copper.</item>
                           </list>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Linnen-cloth,</hi> with all ſorts of
<hi>Linnen-drapery</hi> counterfeit to thoſe which are made in the ſayd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient prouinces.</p>
                           <list>
                              <item>Fine threed, called Spinall.</item>
                              <item>Sowing threed, of all colours.</item>
                              <item>Table-clothes, and Napkins.</item>
                              <item>Woollen clothes.</item>
                              <item>Al maner of Pictures, either in oile or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</item>
                              <item>Lace of threed, or Silke.</item>
                              <item>Narrow canuaſes, &amp; Tapiſtries of al ſorts.</item>
                           </list>
                           <p>All maner of ſmal Haberdaſherrie-wares, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit to thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are made in the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prouinces.</p>
                           <list>
                              <item>Tykes, or Quiltes for bed and feather.</item>
                           </list>
                           <p>And to th'entent the ſaid wares be known, to be the workmanſhip of the ſaid obedient Countries, they ſhall be verified by ſignes of ſuch perſons, as by my ſeale, &amp; my ſaid brother &amp; ſiſter therunto ſhal be deputed which ſhalbe giuen to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal require it, without paying any thing therefore, vpon paine that thoſe which ſhalbe found to be without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid my ſigne or mark, or knowne to be other countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, ſhalbe confiſcated &amp; made good lawful priſe.</p>
                           <p n="8">
                              <pb facs="tcp:13082:7"/>8 I Ordaine, that in my ſayd Kingdomes ſhall not bee ſuffered to come nor bee brought in thoſe Marchandiſes following, without the Seale of my Brother and Siſter, and the Paſport or War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of thoſe which wee ſhall appoint thereunto. But it is withall to bee vnderſtood that the ſayde Seale and Paſport ſhall be giuen them <hi>gratis,</hi> and without any coſt.</p>
                           <list>
                              <item>Buckarums.</item>
                              <item>Bayes.</item>
                           </list>
                           <p>Dyed and dreſſed in the ſaid obedient Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the which aboue the aforeſaide Seale, and Paſport, ſhall bring with them a priuat Seale from the place where they are dyed.</p>
                           <list>
                              <item>Nayles, and all manner of Iron-works.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <item>Molten VVaxe.</item>
                              <item>Sheepe Skinnes.</item>
                              <item>Buff-skinnes.</item>
                              <item>Fuſtians.</item>
                           </list>
                           <p>All manner of Marchandiſes, and ſmal wares, comming from <hi>Norinbregh.</hi> (To wit:)</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Of all ſorts.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>Spangles and graine worke of Glaſſe.</item>
                                 <item>Copper curtaine Rings.</item>
                                 <item>Sayle Needles.</item>
                                 <item>Al manner of Spectacles.</item>
                                 <item>Scalles, or Ballances.</item>
                                 <item>Buttons.</item>
                                 <item>Pincers, and Nayles for
<hi>Shoomakers.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:13082:7"/>
                                 <item>Chafing-diſhes of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Horne for Lanthornes.</item>
                                 <item>Glew of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Matches for Gunnes.</item>
                                 <item>White waxe.</item>
                                 <item>Claſpes and Eyes of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Tape of all faſhions.</item>
                                 <item>Strings for all Inſtruments.</item>
                                 <item>Tallow Candels.</item>
                                 <item>Waxe to ſeale Letters.</item>
                                 <item>Chamblets of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Bed-pannes.</item>
                                 <item>Clockes.</item>
                                 <item>Broken clockes.</item>
                                 <item>Belles of Mettall.</item>
                                 <item>Hogs Briſtles for <hi>Shoomakers.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Small Bels of al ſorts of mettall</item>
                                 <item>Pad-lockes of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Nayles of mettall.</item>
                                 <item>Shooing-hornes of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Candleſticks of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Sawes.</item>
                                 <item>Whiſſels of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Pennes or quilles to write.</item>
                                 <item>All manner of printed Images vpon Paper.</item>
                                 <item>Looking Claſſes, of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Tinne-foile,</item>
                                 <item>Writings, Boxes, or Cabinets of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Inck-hornes of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Bruſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                       <desc>•…</desc>
                                    </gap>es of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Horne bottels of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:13082:8"/>
                                 <item>Buckles for Girdles, of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Carued Images of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Wyer of mettall.</item>
                                 <item>Wyer of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Inſtruments of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Copper in rolles.</item>
                                 <item>Flaxe of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Table-bookes.</item>
                                 <item>All manner of Fyles.</item>
                                 <item>Maskes of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Wrought Engliſh Alabaſter of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Mettals wrought of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Millan ſceanes.</item>
                                 <item>Gold, and Siluer to guild.</item>
                                 <item>Counterfeit gold, of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Lace of Cruel, of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Lead wrought of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Preſſes, and wooden liſtes, or ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Horſe-haire.</item>
                                 <item>Weights of marke of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Watches or ſmal clocks of al ſorts</item>
                                 <item>Beades of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Wheeles of all ſorts of mettall.</item>
                                 <item>Smal nailes for ſtooles or chaires.</item>
                                 <item>Steeles of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Cabidge-ſeede.</item>
                                 <item>Caffas, and of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Hatbands of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Toonges and ſhoouels of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Bone wrought of all ſorts.</item>
                                 <item>Broken mettall of all ſorts.</item>
                              </list>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <pb facs="tcp:13082:8"/>And my will is, that theſe Marchandiſes that ſhall come with the ſaid Seale and Paſport, ſhall bee free and exempt from the ſaide duetie of 30. in the 100 and all ſuch as ſhall ſhew themſelues with the ſaid Paſport and Seale, before my Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, Cuſtomers, or to the perſons which I ſhal appoint thereunto, in my Hauens and Ports, may freely trafficke vpon the ſale of ſuch commodities, paying only the ordinarie duties, without that any hinderance ſhall be done vnto them by any, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall be giuen vnto them all aſſiſtance, at the hands of the Iuſtices. And all Marchandiſe that ſhall not come with the ſayd Seale and Warrant, ſhall pay the aforeſayde duetie of 30. in the
100.</p>
                           <p n="9">9 And to yeeld the trade of Marchandiſes the more eaſie our will is, that the Captaine or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of what Ship ſoeuer, as ſoone as hee ſhall be aryued, ſhall immediatly deliuer vp, his carga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin, or contents of his lading, of the Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſes or Packs which he ſhall haue brought, with their markes and declaration to whom they are directed, vnto the Iuſtices of the Hauens for the which he ſhall be fraighted, the which being done, he ſhall bee permitted to diſcharge his Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſes and deliuer them vnto their owners, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whome they ſhall belong. And if in caſe any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt or treſpaſſe be found to bee vſed againſt my orders, thoſe which ſhall haue receiued ſuch Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes, ſhall be conſtrained to make good the vallew thereof, without that in this behalfe any hinderance or moleſtation ſhall bee done vnto the ſaide Shippes, Captaines, or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Shippes, the which ſhall freely <pb facs="tcp:13082:9"/>be ſuffered to lade and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>urne, vnleſſe they haue themſelues concealed the ſame and beene partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant in the deceit and falſhood.</p>
                           <p n="10">10 And to the end that there be a difference, and a diſtinction betweene our enemies &amp; thoſe which are withdrawn from their lawfull obedience and will ſtil continue in their errors, and betweene our good Vaſſals and Subiects of the ſayd <hi>Neither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands:</hi> and of all others that will trade freely and ſecurely within thſe our Realmes, and that deſires in ſinceritie without fraude or guile to enioy this grace and benefite.</p>
                           <p>And to the ende that the Shippes, Shipper, Marchants, and other perſons of like ſort and qualitie, at this preſence holding their reſidence in the aforenamed Prouices of <hi>Holand</hi> &amp;
<hi>Zeland,</hi> and other being out of the obedience of my aforenamed Brother and Siſter, may be knowne by my Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, Generals of the Armies, Gallyes and all other ſorts of Ships of Warre, I am content and command: That in bringing Paſport in due man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and forme, from my aforenamed Brother and Siſter, or from the perſons which wee, and they ſhall appoint thereunto, in the aforeſayde Lands, ſhall freely, and frankely paſſe, enter, remaine, deale, and quietly and freely exerciſe their trade, according to the Lawes and cuſtomes of theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forenamed Realmes, by vertue of the aforeſayde Paſſeport, without offering them any let or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance, but that all ayde, fauour and aſſiſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen them, and that they be defended againſt all enemies, as well Pyrats as Armyes at ſea which ſhould ſeeke to diſturbe this their free trade, and <pb facs="tcp:13082:9"/>that as well in theſe my ſaide Realmes, as in the ſaid obedient Prouinces of my Brother and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, &amp; the ſaid Paſports ſhal be giuen vnto al ſuch as ſhall require them, without any delay, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking any duetie or other thing whatſoeuer.</p>
                           <p n="11">11 And to the ende that it may bee knowne with what aſſurance they ſhall remaine and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe their trade, in theſe my ſayd Realmes, all ſuch as ſhall intend to remaine and trade therein, by vertue of this preſent Edict, and how well they ſhall be receiued, and how ſecure their perſons and goods ſhall be therein: I promiſe vpon my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly word; that ouer and aboue th'accompliſhment of all the Premiſſes aboue written, that if at any time it were found conuenient, or that vnto me it might ſeeme good to change, or recall this my ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, they ſhall be warned thereof a yeere before hand, that within the ſaid time they may depart freely and ſecurely with their goods and diſpoſe of their matters, and to tranſport themſelues to ſuch places as they ſhall deſire, and thoſe which ſhall be abſent from thence, may be able in like ſort, to diſpoſe of al their goods within the aforeſaid terme of one yeere, as to themſelues ſhall ſeeme moſt meete and conuenient, without that either in the one or in the other any let ſhall bee done vnto them.</p>
                           <p n="12">12 And for the accompliſhment of what is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, touching the aforenamed trade of Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, I commande and ordaine all Iuſtices and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of theſe my Realmes, that they ſuffer to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in all the Hauens thereof all ſorts of Shippes, Shippers, and Marchandiſes of the aforeſaide <pb facs="tcp:13082:10"/>Prouinces of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Seland,</hi> &amp; other their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, alſo of the Subiects of all Princes, Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates and Common-weales, my Friends and Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trals, which ſhall come with Paſport from my ſaid Brother and Siſter, or from the perſons which I, and they ſhall appoint thereunto, and that they permit them to enter, remaine, and exerciſe their trade, freely and frankly, following the orders and cuſtomes of my aforenamed Reamls: maintaining and framing themſelues in all things, according to the tenor of this my preſent Edict, without doing there againſt in any maner: the which I command to be proclaimed, and publiſhed with the accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſolemnities, as well in my Court, as in all the Cities, Townes, Villages, and Hauens of my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forenamed Realmes of Spaine, and the Ilands thereof, to the ende that it may come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of euery one.</p>
                           <p>And all what therein is contained, be perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to be mainetained, performed, and obſerued, as the like ſhall be done by all perſons to whom it may appertaine. Vpon paine of falling into my heauie indignation, and others reſerued to my ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitration, whereof I haue cauſed theſe preſence to be made.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Signed with my owne hand, and Sealed with my Priuie Seale, and Subſcribed by <hi>Andreas</hi> de <hi>Prada,</hi> my Secretarie of State.</signed> 
                              <dateline>Giuen in <hi>Valladolid,</hi>
                                 <date>the 27. of <hi>February.</hi>
1603.</date>
                              </dateline>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:13082:10"/>
               <head> By the Arch-dukes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd deliuering of our preſents, to follow and put in execution, the good and mercifull intent of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forenamed Maieſtie: Wee graunt, and giue leaue and licence, to al and euery one, as well our Subiects, (although there were of the aforenamed Iles of <hi>Holland</hi> and
<hi>Zeland,</hi> and other Prouinces, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen from our alleageance) as alſo vnto all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of what Princes and Common-weales, and of what qualitie, Nation, or condition ſoeuer they bee, our Friends, or Neutrals, after the publication heereof, to bring &amp; diſcharge in our Lands on this ſide beeing vnder our obedience, either thorough the Hauens thereof or through the Hauens, which at this inſtant are held and occupied, by thoſe of our aforenamed Ilands, or by the way of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and
<hi>Germany,</hi> as well by themſelues, as by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of perſons, all ſorts of Marchandiſes, and all other things whatſoeuer or howſoeuer they be brought, or that they ſhall drawe out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and dominions of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the which we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, as well in entering as in going out, to bee free and francke from all dueties, which haue beene rayſed, impoſed, and augmented thereupon, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe thirtie yeeres, ſo far forth that they haue not neither ſhall not, either directly or indirectly pay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impoſitions, cuſtomes or other dueties, in what nature ſoeuer, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aforeſaid diſobedient Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces nor vnto our enemies, vpon the paine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hauing paid any ſuch duties, they ſhalbe forfeit &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fiſcated
<pb facs="tcp:13082:11"/>to wit, onely ſuch as ſhall haue payde the ſame.</p>
               <p>In like maner, &amp; vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame condition, we giue leaue &amp; licence vnto al perſons of what Nation
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer of our friends, &amp; Neutrals with the ſame free<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome &amp; libertie, to bring into the Hauens of our o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bedience, &amp; alſo to tranſport from thence thorough what place ſoeuer all manner of Marchandiſes: onely excepted theſe, which his Maieſtie by his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Edict doth prohibite, becauſe they are not made nor wrought in theſe obedient Prouinces, being thoſe ſame which are ſpecified in the ſeuenth Article of his royall Commandement aboue inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, forbidding, &amp; interdicting, that neither direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nor indirectly, nor by any meanes whatſoeuer, they be not brought in the aforeſaid Lands of our obedience: Vpon paine of confiſcation, and that the tranſgreſſors of this Ordinance ſhall be pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with all rigor.</p>
               <p>And to the ende that each one, the better may enioy this grace and benefite of his Maieſtie, and of vs, and make their voyages towards the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>Spaine:</hi> Wee will at all times cauſe to be giuen and granted the Paſports, which they ſhall neede for their ſecuritie, at what times they ſhall require them free and francke, without paying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny duetie therefore.</p>
               <p>In like manner, touching the Marchandiſes, which his Maieſtie by this his ſayd Edict are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, &amp; forbiddeth not to enter in his realms, vnleſſe they were made in the Lands of our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or haue paſſed there thorough with cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the perſons, the which in his Maieſties, and our behalfe thereunto ſhall be appointed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb facs="tcp:13082:11"/>to the tenor of the afore-named Edict, to the en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that the ſame doe not diſturbe the courſe of the trade, and that all ſuch perſons, freely ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come without any peril or danger, in the aforena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Realmes, the ſaid Certificate, or Warrant ſhall be graunted vnto them, yea, without paying any thing for the ſame, by the handes of
<hi>Iohn de Gauna,</hi> or of ſuch other perſons, as we ſhall name there vnto, to the aſſiſtance of thoſe which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie ſhall depute, and appoint thereunto, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid certificate or Warrant ſigned by them both, it ſhall bee valeable, and other wayes not.</p>
               <p>And to the end that, that is aboue written haue his whole and lawfull effect, and that each one, ſo much the better, may know our good heart and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, we giue leaue and licence, to all trading Marchants, Shippers or their Factors, Officers, Handecrafts-men, &amp; all other perſons of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he lands withdrawne from our obedience, to returne into theſe of our alleageance, and there to liue and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy theſe goods being in the hands of the Fiſcall, in ſuch maner as at this preſent they are, without power to ſell or allienate the ſame, vnleſſe with our conſent, ſo farre foorth they maintaine the Lawes of the aforeſaid Lands: and ſuch perſons as ſhall come in this manner, wee will receiue them into our grace and mercie, with vtter abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhment of all forepaſſed matters, the which is to be vnderſtood, to be done, in regard of ſuch as ſhal haue abſented themſelues by reaſon of the wars, without any other priuate offence, and that ſhall not preſeuer nor intermeddle further therein.</p>
               <p>Therefore, wee will and commaund you, that <pb facs="tcp:13082:12"/>immediatly and without delay, you are to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh theſe preſents with all ſolemnitie, throughout all the Townes and places of our Countreys and Countie of <hi>Artoys,</hi> where the Proclamations and Edicts are uſually publiſhed, to the ende they may come to the knowledge of each.</p>
               <p>Ordaying and Commanding, vnto all Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Iuſticies, Officers and men of Lawe of your iuriſdicting the ſtrickt obſeruance, and mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance thereof, vſing all good entertainment, and kinde vſage, vnto all ſuch as ſhall bee willing to accept of this ordinance and fauour, receiuing them in their Townes and Offices reſpectiuely, although that at this preſent, they doe holde or haue helde their reſidence, in the Prouinces di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from our obedience, or in any other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo farrefoorth as they behaue themſelues ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Lawes and Cuſtomes there vſed, euen as the like is done by theſe which are reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the places of our ſaid obeiſſaunce, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the charge, that before hand ſhall preſent themſelues, vnto the Magiſtrates of the Citties, and Townes where they ſhall deſire to dwell, without that they ſhall neede at any time to ſhewe any other diligence nor duetie, neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nor after.</p>
               <p>And all this to bee effected, without dooing of ſuffering to be done vnto them, for the fore paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed matters: any trouble, diſturbance or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, vpon paine that the trangreſſors ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure our heauie indignitie and to bee rigourouſly puniſhed, for that ſuch our pleaſure is.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:13082:12"/>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen in our Cittie of
<hi>Bruſſels,</hi> vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> our Counter-Seale: Imprinted thereon in forme of Edict.
<date>The fifth day of <hi>Aprill.</hi> 1603.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Signed, by the <hi>Arch-dukes</hi> and their Counſaile, and ſubſcribed.</signed>
               <signed>And thereon ſtandeth imprinted their High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Counter-Seale, in forme of Edict.</signed>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <p>The like Edicts, <hi>mutatis mutandis,</hi> haue beene diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched in the Netherlandiſh-tongue, for <hi>Gelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Malynes:</hi> And in the French tongue for
<hi>Luxenbrough, Artoys, Hainault, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, Lille, Douay,</hi> and <hi>Vrchids, Tournay,</hi> and <hi>Dour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſay,</hi> and
<hi>Valencienne.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
